Guide to the Wesley Works archive, 1676-1996 and undated, bulk 1724-1791, 1960-1996 RL.01368
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters Series (Volumes 25-31), 1721-1996 and undated, 15 boxes
  - General Planning Subseries, 1724-1996 and undated
    Following Indexes and Logs are several folder groups of reproductions of thousands of Wesley letters, both outgoing and incoming, compiled from various sources and organized in various ways: Letters from Printed Sources, Letters by Archive, Letters by Correspondent, and Letters by Chronology.
    The last three groups contain photocopies and microfilm printouts of hundreds of manuscript letters from and to JW, many of which have not yet appeared in printed form. There are far too many to cite here individually, but some of these are noted in the finding aid, with preference being given to those more difficult to access, such as those from smaller archives and those that have never been published in either the Telford or Abingdon editions of the Wesley's letters.
    - Acquisition of letters, 1902-1979
      - American book prices, current, 1970-1979 and undated (Box 80)
      - Letters to follow up, 1926-1960 (Box 80)
      - Notes on magazine indexes from 1850-1930, undated (Box 80)
      - Plans to acquire letters--correspondence, 1934, 1947, 1963-1977, 2 folders (Box 80)
      - Sotheby catalogs, 1902-1976 and undated, 2 folders (Box 80)
    - Correspondence, 1754-1800, 1970-1996
      - Baker notes, correspondence, and photocopies of letters, 1754-1800, 1970-1996 (Box 80)
        Includes photocopy, transcription, and discussion of a late (1788) JW letter to Nancy Bolton, privately-held as of the mid-1990s.
      - Baker correspondence, 1952-1995 and undated, 2 folders (Box 118)
      - Campbell, Ted, 1989 (Box 80)
      - International inquiries for institutional holdings, 1974-1975, 3 folders (Box 80)
      - Methodist Archives, 1986-1989 (Box 80)
      - Outler, Albert, 1974 (Box 80)
    - Identification of letters, 1724-1829, 1889-1897, 1936, 1951, 1963-1992
      - Amanuenses and scribes--identifying, 1736-1789, 1978-1985, 2 folders (Box 81)
      - Covers, 1780-1787 (Box 81)
      - Facsimiles taken as originals, 1778, 1992 (Box 81)
      - Finished, 1950-1987 (Box 81)
      - Franks, postmarks, undated (Box 81)
      - Letter seals, 1724-1791, 1951, 1973-1985 and undated, 5 folders (Box 81)
        Photographs, research, and replicas of JW's letter seals; ca. 1724-1791. One folder contains material on the monogram for the Oxford Edition.
      - Letters to identify, 1753-1829, 1889-1897, 1936, 1963-1975 and undated (Box 81)
      - Undated, uncertain, 1757-1783, 1969 (Box 81)
      - Watermarks, 1736-1791 and undated (Box 81)
    - Indexes and logs, circa 1976-1993 and undated
      Related materials: in addition to those gathered here, several other indexes and files of letters to and from John and Charles Wesley can be found in the Frank Baker Papers. In the Writings and Research Series, Writings by Others Subseries, see the extensive, multiply-indexed "Early Methodist Letters," compiled and written by Thomas R. Albin. In the Subject Files Series, Card Files Subseries, see the various files under "Letters" and "Wesley Letters."
      - Database and master list of letters to JW from 1755-1790, 1992-1993 and undated (Box 81)
      - JW letters not appearing in Telford's Edition, 1986 and undated (Box 81)
        Log of Wesley's letters, including recipient and archival source, from 1734-1791. See also "Early log" below
      - Methodist letters--Tom Albin's list, 1989 (Box 81)
      - Notebook: early log of Wesley letters, circa mid-1970s-1980s (Box 81)
      - Pawson, John--log of his letters from 1764-1806, undated (Box 81)
    - Letters by archive, 1725-1830, 1930, 1954-1992
      - Australian correspondence, 1758-1780, 1954-1988 (Box 81)
        Typed transcription of JW letter, 1780 Sept. 30. Photocopies and transcriptions of two JW letters to Jonathan Pritchard, 1758 Mar. 25 and 1772 Feb. 27.
      - JW letters: BR/C-D [i.e., Didsbury College, now Wesley College], 1750-1830, 1930 (Box 82)
        Approximately 50 letters, mainly from JW, but also from William Grimshaw, Joseph Benson, and others..
      - Bristol letters requested in mail [Wesley's Chapel], 1769, 1790, 1992 (Box 82)
        Photocopies of two non-Telford letters: 1789 Aug. 28, JW to Mrs. [Charles] Wesley; and 1790 Oct. 22, JW to Mr. York.
      - London P.R.O. [Public Record Office, London], 1736-1777, 1964-1977 (Box 82)
      - Methodist Archives, John Rylands University of Manchester, MS. 170--photocopy from Charles Wesley notebook, 1755-1756 (Box 82)
        Related materials: other photocopies of MS. 170, which may cover different portions, can be found in the Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files, Wesley Family Files, John Wesley Letters.
      - Methodist Archives, John Rylands University of Manchester--microfilm photographs and photocopies, 1725-1788, 1978, 2 folders (Box 82)
        Group of seventeen letters to JW, identified by FB and alphabetized by sender.
      - Moravian Archives - London, 1745-1748 (oversize), 2 folders (Box 84)
    - Letters by chronology, 1724-1790
      - Letters from JW, 1736-1789 (Box 84)
      - Letters to JW, 1724-1734, 2 folders (Box 84)
        Approximately 108 photocopied letters, from, among others: Samuel Wesley, Sr., Susannah Wesley, Samuel Wesley, Jr., Emilia Wesley, Kezia Wesley, Martha Wesley, Hetty Wesley, John Clayton, and Benjamin Ingham.
      - Letters to JW, 1735-1745, 6 folders (Box 85)
        Approximately 220 photocopied letters, from, among others: Charles Wesley, Samuel Wesley, Jr., George Whitefield, James Hutton, Benjamin Ingham, Susannah Designe, and Selina Hastings, Countess of Huntingdon.
      - Letters to JW, 1746-1769, 5 folders (Box 86)
        Approximately 300 photocopied letters, from, among others: John Bennet, Alexander Coates, Jane Cooper, Philip Doddridge, John Fletcher, Martha Hall, Selina Hastings, Countess of Huntingdon, Samuel Lloyd, Sarah Ryan, Charles Wesley, and George Whitefield.
      - Letters to JW, 1770-1781, 5 folders (Box 87)
        Approximately 280 photocopied letters, from, among others: Thomas Austen, Samuel Bardsley, John Crook, John Fletcher, Thomas Hanby, the Countess of Huntingdon, Elizabeth Ritchie, Charles Wesley, and Thomas Wride (several lengthy manuscript letters).
      - Letters to JW, 1782-1790, 2 folders (Box 88)
        Approximately 120 photocopied letters, from, among others: Francis Asbury, Samuel Bradburn, Thomas Carlill, Thomas Coke, Ezekiel Cooper, John Fletcher, Mary Gilbert, Alexander Mather, Hester Roe/Hester Rogers, Sarah (Sally) Wesley, Thomas Wride, and Francis Wrigley.
    - Letters by correspondent, 1736-1791, 1942-1994
      - AW and MW, letters to, 1744-1758 (Box 82)
        Note: From "Holy Oyle."
      - Bennet, John--letter book, 1749-1757, 1942, 1978 and undated, 2 folders (Box 82)
        Photocopies from both the original letter-book and from the transcription made by Marmaduke Riggall in the 1920s.
        Related materials: the original of Riggall's full transcription is housed in the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, Volumes Series, Writings Subseries.
      - Blackwell, Ebenezer, 1751-1762, 1870-1895, 1951-1976 (Box 88)
      - Bolton, Ann (to), 1768-1791, 1959-1969 (Box 82)
        Photocopies from various print and manuscript sources, all previously published. The folder group for Bolton in the Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files Series also contains copies of Bolton's letters to JW, as well as extensive photocopy of the manuscript of Bolton's journal.
      - Bredin, John, 1784 Feb. 6 (Box 82)
        Note by FB as non-Telford.
      - Dale, Peggy (to, printed), 1765-1769 (Box 82)
      - Gibbes, Agnes (to), 1783-1785, 1968-1977 (Box 88)
        Mainly copies of Wesley's manuscript letters to Gibbes, from Public Records Office, London.
      - Haimes, John, 1778 (Box 82)
      - Landey, Thomas--1752, 1994 (Box 82)
        To JW as copied by Charles Wesley, 1752 July 29; and FB's correspondence and notes on Landey and the Wesleys.
      - Mallet, Sarah (to), 1788 (Box 82)
      - Ritchie, Elizabeth, 1774-1788 (Box 82)
        Photocopies of thirty-two letters, all but two from originals in the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism, Wesley Family Division.
      - "John Smith," 1745, 1975 and undated, 2 folders (Box 82)
      - Sparrow, Samuel, 1772-1773 (Box 82)
      - Zinzendorf, Count, 1736-1740, 1974-1977 (Box 82)
      - Unaddressed letter from JW, 1773 Feb. 12; and FB correspondence, 1990 (Box 82)
    - Letters from printed sources, 1758-1770, 1831, 1866, 1977
      - Letters to periodicals, 1762, 1770, 1977 (Box 83)
      - Telford Letters, 1758-1766 (Box 83)
      - Undated letters in print, 1831, 1866 (Box 83)
    - Other documents and letters, 1751-1811, 1843, 1861, 1900-1929, 1980
      - Brackenbury, R. C., 1811 and undated (Box 83)
      - Merryweather, G. (Melbourne), 1843 (Box 83)
      - Moore, Henry, A Plain Account of the Conduct of Mr. Whitehead Respecting Mr. Wesley's..., 1791-1809 (Box 83)
      - Stampe, George, undated (Box 83)
      - Miscellaneous, 1751-1790, 1861, 1900-1929, 1980 (Box 83)
    - Copies of MSS Letters both by and to JW, 1720-1776, 32 folders (Box 116)
    - Copies of MSS Letters both by and to JW, 1777-1791, 15 folders (Box 117)
    - Copies of letters in newspapers, 1756-1765 (Box 117)
    - Copies of MSS letters, non-JW correspondence, 18 folders (Box 118)
  - Volumes Subseries, 1775, 1977-1994 and undated
    Correspondence, typescripts, proofs, and other materials for Letters I: 1721-1739 and Letters II: 1740-1755 (Volumes 25 and 26, respectively); and a small amount of preparatory material for Letters III: 1756-1765 (Volume 27, in preparation).
    - Letters I: 1721-1739 (Volume 25) correspondence, typescripts, and proofs
      - Correspondence, 1977-1979 (Box 83)
      - Miscellaneous papers, Vols. 25-26, 1775, 1977 and undated (Box 83)
      - Translation of difficult letter excerpts, 1977 (Box 83)
      - Introduction typescript, incomplete, undated (Box 83)
      - Edited typescript, undated, Folders 1-4 of 5 (Box 83)
      - Edited typescript, undated, Folder 5 of 5 (Box 89)
      - Typescript photocopy, undated, 6 folders (Box 89)
      - Introduction typescript "B," edited, circa 1979 and undated, 2 folders (Box 90)
      - Typescript "B," edited, circa 1978-1979, 5 folders (Box 90)
      - OUP proofs edited by Baker, 1978-1979 and undated, Folder 1 of 3 (Box 90)
      - OUP proofs edited by Baker, 1978-1979 and undated, Folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 91)
      - OUP (Oxford University Press) proofs--Introduction notes and revisions, 1978, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 91)
      - Oversize OUP proofs--Introduction notes and revisions, 1978, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 88)
      - OUP proofs--appendix, circa 1978 (Box 88)
      - OUP proofs, edited and corrected, 1979, 3 folders (Box 91)
      - List of corrections, 1979 undated (Box 91)
      - Substitute pages, Vols. 25-26, 1979-1980 (Box 91)
    - Letters II: 1740-1755 (Volume 26) correspondence, typescripts, and proofs
      - Research, correspondence, typescripts, 1978-1979 (Box 91)
      - Proofs--correspondence with Baker, 1978-1981 (Box 91)
      - Typescript, copy edited, circa 1980, Folder 1 of 6 (Box 91)
      - Typescript, copy edited, circa 1980, Folders 2-6 of 6 (Box 92)
      - Edited typescript "B," undated, Folders 1-2 of 6 (Box 92)
      - Edited typescript "B," undated, Folders 3-6 of 6 (Box 93)
      - Typescript of appendix: Wesley's correspondence, undated (Box 93)
      - Indices of Wesley's correspondents, 1978 and undated (Box 93)
      - Early OUP proofs, 1980-1981, 4 folders (Box 94)
      - Later proofs, undated, 2 folders (Box 94)
      - List of corrections, undated (Box 94)
      - Corrections and additions, Vols. 25-26; correspondence, typescript, 1993-1994 (Box 94)
    - Letters III: 1756-1765 (Volume 27) correspondence and research
      - Appendix revision, 1992 (Box 94)
      - Correspondence, 1994 (Box 94)
      - Word lists, 1988 (Box 94)
- Bibliography Series (Volumes 33-34), 1710-1791, 1841, 1947-1993 and undated, 10 boxes
  The penultimate unit of the Bicentennial Edition is represented in the Bibliography Series. Aside from the Letters, this was the only other portion for which Frank Baker served as the original unit editor. Planned as Volumes 33-34 but left incomplete at his death, the Bibliography was only one instantiation of a topic on which he labored for several decades: documenting the publishing history of the editions of their writings that appeared in print during the lifetimes of John and Charles Wesley. Independently of his work on the WWEP, and yet also in preparation for it, Baker had already published A Union Catalogue of the Publications of John and Charles Wesley in 1966. Although this title and the work-in-progress he called "A Descriptive and Analytical Bibliography" may at first sound like two names for more or less the same thing, the latter is in fact a radically different work. The words "descriptive" and "analytical" in the title were not added lightly: each publication with a completed entry in the bibliography is taken up and considered in a full-length essay. Baker of course provides the expected bibliographic details for all editions to appear in Wesley's lifetime, derives the stemma or publishing genealogy of each work, and lists holdings around the world, just as in the Union Catalogue. But here he does far more. He also discusses each work's place in the Wesley canon, considers everything from how and why it came to be written and published, to its reception history, to the ways Wesley used and adapted it in successive printings over the years. In short, the drafts and typescripts collected here, though uncompleted, go well beyond "bibliography" or even "annotated bibliography" as those terms are generally conceived. They set out to describe in full a publishing phenomenon that spanned two-thirds of the 18th century: the life in print of a speaker, writer, editor, and abridger whose works appeared in more than four thousand editions in his own lifetime alone.
  Arranged in four subseries: General Planning; Printers and Printing; Stemmata and Texts; and Typescripts. Because his work on the "Descriptive and Analytical Bibliography" required Baker to consult so many thousands of editions of works by John and Charles Wesley, this series has an extremely complex relationship not only with other series in the current collection but also with other collections at Duke. The outline provided below is not exhaustive in explicating these relationships, but does provide guidance about when to expect to find related materials at Duke, and where to search. Frank Baker was the original unit editor for Volumes 33 and 34, and authored almost all the original material in this series, the bulk of which dates to the 1970s and 1980s. Unit editors were Page Thomas and Richard P. Heitzenrater.
  For a general overview of all the Frank Baker collections at Duke, see Related Materials in this inventory. To access all pertinent information at Duke on particular publications by JW, see also the following series/subseries and collections as applicable:
  For initial bibliographic information on a particular title, see both the Stemmata and Texts Subseries and the Typescripts Subseries in the current series. In addition, further information can often be found in the Series/Subseries corresponding to the volume in which the title appeared (or is planned to appear). As an extreme but instructive example, all of the following materials can be found about the single sermon Awake, Thou That Sleepest: a 23-page essay and stemma in the Typescripts Subseries below: an additional folder of notes and rough drafts in the Stemmata and Texts subseries; and more notes, including photocopies of over fifty editions from libraries around the world, in the Sermons Series, Stemmata Subseries.
  In addition to the above, see also the Frank Baker Photocopies Collection (Divinity School) for other possible photocopies, transcriptions, and notes on stemma.
  See the Frank Baker Microfilm Collection (Divinity School) for microfilm of manuscript and printed collections from around the world. For the provenance of these microfilm, including history of acquisition and correspondence with the archives involved, see the Frank Baker Papers, Libraries and Archives Series. (Rubenstein Library)
  See the printed materials division of the Frank Baker Collection of Wesleyana and British Methodism (Rubenstein Library) for original editions Baker may have used in his research. These items may be searched in the online catalog.
  Also see the Frank Baker Papers for more materials on any of the following topics: for the closely related work, A Union Catalogue of the Publications of John and Charles Wesley, see the Writings and Research Series, Union Catalogue Subseries; for topics listed in the Printers and Printing subseries below, see the unpublished essay Printers' Flowers as Bibliographic Evidence in Eighteenth Century Britain in the Writings and Research Series, Unpublished Writings Subseries; for indexes of Wesley's writings, including certain volumes of the Bicentennial Edition, see the Subject Files Series, Card Files Subseries.
  - General Planning Subseries, 1961-1994 and undated
    Several folders of general information, mainly brief with the exception of the "Preparatory handbook," which contains extensive details about how Baker prepared and updated the bibliography as he worked. Arranged alphabetically by topic.
    - Bibliography guidelines, 1967 (Box 95)
    - Bibliography notes for background, 1966-1967 (Box 95)
    - Bibliography stemmata, typology, etc., 1978-1984 (Box 95)
    - Miscellaneous correspondence and notes, 1968-1994, and undated (Box 95)
    - Preparatory handbook, A-Z (working copy and fair copy), 1983, 2 folders (Box 95)
    - Variants for Wesley bibliography, 1961-1962 (Box 95)
    - Works mistakenly attributed to JW, 1961, 1993 (Box 95)
  - Printers and Printing Subseries: Notes and Research, 1710-1791, 1841, 1947-1993 and undated
    A collection of folders based on the subjects of bibliography, the printing of JW's writings, and printers' flowers and ornaments. Regarding the last topic, there is much research and unpublished writing files as "Printers' Flowers as Bibliographic Evidence," to be found in the Frank Baker Papers, Writings and Research Series, Unpublished Writings Subseries.
    - American Methodist imprints, 1965, and undated (Box 95)
    - American printers: James Adams of Wilmington, 1770 (Box 95)
    - Annual register, 1758-1759 (Box 95)
    - Appendices, 1984, and undated (Box 95)
    - Ascribed to Wesley, Nos. 670-699, undated (Box 95)
    - Bibliography of American Literature, 1955, and undated (Box 95)
    - Bibliography: catalogues and announcements in periodicals, undated (Box 95)
    - Book Account, 1789 (Box 95)
    - Book Room, 1791, 1842-1844, 1991 (Box 95)
    - Book sellers and advertisements, 1744 (Box 95)
    - Bristol Journal, 1757, 1968-1969 (Box 95)
    - Bristol newspaper notes, 1742-1743, 1956, 1973 (Box 95)
    - Catalogues of publishing (JW), 1746-1789, 1989, Folder 1 of 3 (Box 95)
    - Catalogues of publishing (JW), 1746-1789, 1989, Folders 2-3 of 3 (Box 96)
    - Catalogues: non-Wesley, 1754-1798 (Box 96)
    - Covers of books or magazines, with contents, letters, advertisements, etc., Nos. 850-867, 1783 (Box 96)
    - Delacolonge, 1773 (Box 96)
    - Engravings, 1735 (Box 96)
    - Flowers - Printers', 1710-1799, 1960-1982, and undated, 11 folders (Box 96)
      Printers: Baskerville, Caslon, Cottrell, Fry, James, Stephenson, Wilson. Includes folder of selections, duplicates, and a photocopied book on printings. Texts photocopied from early and late 18th century. Baker's notes date from the 1960s-1980s.
    - Flowers - Printers', 1732-1779 and undated, 37 folders (Box 119)
      Printers:: Calson, Cock, Pica, and American printers' flowers. Texts photocopied from early and late 18th century.
    - Fournier, Modéles des Caracteres de L'Imprimerie, 1742 (Box 96)
    - Hawes, Robert, 1773-1780, 1983 (Box 96)
    - Imprints, undated (Box 96)
    - List of publications in collection, undated (Box 96)
    - List of standard bibliographies, undated (Box 96)
    - Lloyd's Evening Post, 1764-1765, 1988 (Box 96)
    - London Chronicle, 1757-1791 (Box 96)
    - MS Alterations, 1747 (Box 96)
    - Monthly Review, 1749-1789 (Box 96)
    - Newcastle Journal, 1743-1747, 1991 (Box 97)
    - Ornaments, 1738-1771, 1985, 3 folders (Box 97)
    - Ornaments, 1719-1779, 54 folders (Box 120)
    - Press figures, undated (Box 97)
    - Printers and booksellers: Foundery, New Room, New Chapel, undated (Box 97)
    - Printers (countries), 1988-1993 and undated, 5 folders (Box 97)
      Series of notes, mainly undated, on printers and printing in America, England, Ireland, Scotland, and Wales.
    - Printers' illustrations, 1984 and undated, 2 folders (Box 97)
      Alphabetical file--photocopies of hundreds of 18th century printers' flowers and ornaments.
    - Printing trade, 1986-1991 (Box 97)
    - Published by others, undated (Box 97)
    - Publishing histories, 1968, 1986 and undated (Box 97)
      Publishing histories for various JW writings, but mainly sermons. Contains long letter and some 40 pages of notes from FB to Albert Outler, 1968, on the histories of various sermons. This work does not appear to be duplicated in the Sermons Series itself.
    - Reilly, Dictionary of Ornaments, undated (Box 97)
    - Rosart, The Type Specimen of Jacques François Rosart, 1973 (Box 97)
    - Savage, William, Dictionary of the Art of Printing, 1841 (Box 97)
    - Simon, Oliver, Introduction to Typography, 1947 (Box 97)
    - Works sponsored, undated (Box 97)
  - Stemmata and Texts Subseries, 1733-1759 and circa 1960s-1980s
    Contains Baker's research on individual publication histories of the first 94 works to be listed in the Bibliography, plus various work on scattered higher-numbered entries. Most folders contain photocopies of multiple editions of these works, Baker's drafts and notes for the individual publication history of the work, and an outline of the stemma. In theory, Baker's writing and notes here should match the more polished versions to be found in the full 1981 typescript to be found in the next subseries; in practice, though, no comparison has been made, so there are likely to be handwritten notes here that are not included in the fair copy typescript. For this subseries, due to the high proportion of partial and full photocopies and transcribed materials, the dates in the box list reflect only the initial publication dates that Baker cited for each work. Although no attempt has been made to include dates of all items in each folder, in most cases it can be assumed that materials photocopied from later 18th century editions are included--gathering such editions for evaluation was the point of the research. Baker's own writing and notes are almost all undated, but it the bulk of this work was done by the early 1980s. Arranged in order of the new numbering scheme assigned by Baker for the Bibliography; the equivalent older number, based on the earlier bibliographies of Baker and Richard Green, is indicated in parentheses. Researchers should note that while this list stops at item 94, short of the 106 in the full typescript in the next folder group, it also picks up again with miscellaneous manuscripts for handful of citations above 106.
    - 1. (Green/UC 1) A Collection of Forms of Prayer (1733) (Box 98)
    - 2-3. Norris, John: A Treatise on Christian Prudence (Green/UC 2) and Reflections Upon the Conduct of Human Life (Green/UC 25) (1734) (Box 98)